like to welcome everyone to this
afternoon's press conference at the
deis. We have the number one overall
draft pick for Nano Mendoza, general
manager John Spyitech and head coach
Clint Kubak. We'll begin with some
opening remarks from Mr. Spitech and
then we'll open it up for questions.
>> Okay. Um I want to thank everybody for
coming this afternoon to an exciting day
for the Raiders organization and the Las
Vegas community. The the long mystery
has finally been solved. We got our guy
here and um just want to thank everybody
that was a part of this process in this
building to to arrive to this selection
of Fernando was not a coronation. He
earned it every bit of the way with his
play and the way that he conducted
himself in all of our one-on-one
interactions during the draft process.
So, we're thrilled to welcome Fernando
to Las Vegas. To have his family here
today is really special. I hope it's
been a special 24-ish hours for them. I
know it's been a whirlwind, but we are
thrilled to welcome Fernando Mendoza to
the Las Vegas Raiders.
>> Okay, at this time we'll open up for
questions from the media. We have
microphones in both aisles. Please raise
your hand and state your name and
affiliation.
>> Adam Hill, Las Vegas Review Journal. Uh
Fernando, it's been a long process. You
talked about that the college season,
the draft process, now you're actually
here. Does it kind of feel more real now
that they're in the building and part of
the team? And then the second part, did
you have to apologize to your brother
for snubbing him with the high five
after the draft?
>> Yeah, first of all, with my brother, we
actually had two like kind of like post
celebrations when we got the call and
then when the pick went in and saw any
on TV, but you know, I I I apologize to
him and he knows I love him. So, I I hit
him with a dap and a hug afterwards.
And there's a lot of anticipation coming
to this pick, but now I'm really glad
that all the outside noise is done. I'm
officially a Raider. I'm excited to be
humble and hungry and get to work.
>> For Ronaldando, Ryan McFaten from ESPN.
Uh my question for you, I read that you
trained with Brian Greasie ahead of the
draft. I was curious like what kind of
led to that and what was it like working
with him?
Yeah, Coach Greasie is a great guy and
we both went to the same high school,
Christopher Columbus down in Miami,
Florida. And with him is someone that
that I reached out to because I needed
some guidance on how to become the best
NFL quarterback, not just for like a pro
day or the combine for September when I
actually or September or or when
whatever it is in October, December,
just whenever you know to be an NFL
quarterback.
And with that, we just went over some
general under center concepts and just
installed basic bread and butter
concepts that any any team would have.
So, it was great working with him and he
kind of get gave me an adjustment
because he's been a NFL quarterback
coach in the past.
>> Fernando, department, you and I were
laughing at the combine about you being
an unemployed college kid. You're now a
first round selection with a $55 million
guaranteed deal that's coming on the
table. Has the enormity
of the responsibility and the blessing
hit you yet?
>> Yeah, it's a huge blessing. However, I
feel like I still need to earn it and I
haven't proved anything. The college, my
college career was very blessed and it
was great, very significant career.
However, in the NFL, I'm on the bottom
of the totem pole again. So, I'm really
looking forward to proving it every
single day to everybody in the building.
>> Fernando Ezekiel Tresan on SI. You
mentioned yesterday that you had been
looking into the West Coast offense. I'm
curious what part of the West Coast
offense or what part of your game are
you looking forward to uh improving the
most?
>> I think the part of the West Coast
offense that I found the most
interesting was the run tracks and
especially how important that is off the
system of making sure you're on the
right track for outside zone, getting
the ball deepest as possible to the
running back so you can have the best
vision possible, which then helps out
the offensive line. And I'm always
trying to do my 111th and the offense. I
believe it allows a quarterback to be a
great point guard and such a great
scheme like coach Kubak has and I just
want to do my 111th whether it's handing
the ball off throwing making a check
whatever maybe
Fang Las Vegas Review Journal I was
curious is how much u how much familiar
familiarity excuse me do you have with
Kirk Cousins and his career and what are
you hoping to learn from him? Yeah, I
was blessed this morning and last night.
I was able to get a text from a couple
of guys like Max Crosby, Tyler
Linderbomb, Colton Miller, and Kirk
Cousins. And I'm sure there's been more.
I'm looking forward out to reaching out
to all my new teammates and most of
those guys. It's been a whirlwind in the
past couple hours. But Kirk send me a
really nice text. I'm looking forward to
working with him, learning anything I
can from him and just a great not only
teammates that I'm able to learn from,
but also the great coaches.
>> Uh Clint Ed Granny Review Journal. John
talked about last night the offense and
how he fits when you watch tape and
everything. Where does his skill set
fit? Where do you like him most in your
offense?
>> Yeah, his skill set fits with any
offense in in in pro in professional
football. You know, obviously, uh, the
number one thing that I love about
Fernando is his leadership, the way that
he relates to his teammates and his
ability to win. You know, we're looking
for a competitor, uh, to be our
quarterback. And he's got, uh, you know,
you know, he went 16 and0 last year with
a heck of a team and he led that group.
So, um, love his athleticism, his
ability to throw accurately down the
field. Um, he's very accurate. Um, but
at the end of the day, he's a bright,
intelligent leader.
Harry Ruiz with the Spanish Raider
broadcast for the Raiders. Fernando,
what does the responsibility of being a
Raider mean to you when you look to your
left and you got Jim Plunk at the last
man to win the Super Bowl as the
quarterback for the team and to your
right, you got Fred Bletnikov, the first
Super Bowl MVP in the history of the
franchise. And then you got the Vince
Lombardi trophies right in front of you
as well.
>> It's a huge responsibility, but it's
also a huge honor to honor the legacy.
The Raiders are Coron franchise and the
one of the faces of the NFL and I feel
like again I need to prove it and earn
it every single day. If I you know wear
number 15 this year whether or not that
happens I mean Tom Flores who was able
to coach and win two Super Bowls and
also wear number 15 as a quarterback,
you know, he has cemented that number.
So I feel like every part every corner
you turn you see you know Mr. Plunkett,
Mr. Brown, you know Mr. Allen like
everybody Mr. Valentino and I really
appreciate every all the legends coming
out here today. It means so much to see
the alumni and really shows what what a
first class organization this is. So I'm
stoked and ready to prove it.
>> Hey Fernando uh to your left Omar Ruiz
NFL Network. We know you're a planner,
you're a preparer and and everything you
do. What's going back to your teammates?
What's the sort of plan to connect with
the guys kind of once you get into the
locker room uh here with the Raiders?
Yeah, I think it's familiarity and
especially as a rookie, nothing's given
and my belief that everything is earned.
So, I'm going to come in humble, try to
establish myself as, you know, with my
work ethic and lead by example. By the
end of the day, you know, it's all great
saying these words, but I got to do it.
And so, I'm looking forward to
connecting with them. And I'm just
excited to learn from them as well and
care about them as people.
>> Fernando Mark Anderson, AP. Um, you're
starting this fund. Can you just talk
about what that means to you?
>> The the fight MS.
>> Oh, sorry. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's great. My mom's there in the
back. You know, I can't thank her enough
for everything. So, we started the
Mendoza Family Fund, which we were able
to get a a good donation to starting
off. I've been blessed in my journey.
And I believe one of my pillars and my
identities is giving back and helping
fighting MS giving the community. So,
that was a huge part my identity and
something that our family really wanted
to do.
Raiders.
>> Yeah. I mean, the history of the
Raiders, especially the Hispanic
history, is like no other. I believe
it's probably the most
the Hispanic fan base and legends like
Mr. Plunket, like M Mr. Flores. I mean,
all those legendary Hispanic idols and
cornerstones in the franchise. It it
means a lot as a Cuban American to come
to this franchise and help try to carry
the torch. But again, I got to prove it.
I'm really looking forward to connecting
with the Hispanic community here.
>> Levi Edwards Raiders.com. You were
talking about the alumni presence and
you obviously walk in and you see three
Heismans when you walk in coming off of
a Heisman Trophy win. How did that feel?
And also the sense of that pressure of
winning the Heisman Trophy. Does that
include is that added coming into the
NFL team or is it not anything you
really think about?
>> Yeah, I think it was in the last
chapter. It was a great chapter and
don't get me wrong, the Heisman's an
awesome trophy and I'm really happy that
I won it. However, I thought not I won
it. The team won it. The Indiana team
won it. But that's that's in the past
chapter, but there's a great history of
Heisman Trophy winners here in law in in
that for the Raiders. There's I mean I
think there's around 9 to 11 in the
total history. So that commitment to
excellence that goes not only from the
college but also to the NFL level is
shown by all the Heisman Trophy winners
here. I'm lucky to be a part of it.
Antonio,
well, I definitely understand it. I
would say I have really confident in my
understanding ability. for example, like
repeat back what you said, speaking it.
I still need to get better on I need to
learn every single part of my of my
journey, but I would say but but I will
say I'm I'm, you know, working on
learning my Spanish back in. It was my
first language, but being Hispanic is
everything to me. I believe culture is
the one is a thing that sets a person
and their identity. And I'm lucky enough
to be raised by four CubanAmerican
grandparents and my parents also
instilling the Cuban culture in me. So
it means a lot to be a part of this
Hispanic community. Looking forward to
embracing it at every every moment I
can.
Fernando here in the middle, Jesse
Merrick with Silver and Black Sports
Network. I remember hearing you in some
interviews talking about when you were
looking about where you wanted to
transfer about your brother at Indiana
and that how he was learning and
developing in terms of reading defenses
and stuff like that at a kind of a
different level. I'm curious now in
hindsight in that area what you really
took away that think prepared you the
most for this job now with the Raiders.
>> I think it's the ability to get coached.
The ability to get coached and always
come in with a low ego
and be open to new coaching and that was
a big thing at California. It was a
successful season but coming to Indiana
I realized I had so much more to learn
and I always want to have exponential
growth every single year and that is
made by the process the work ethic and
the inputs I do every single day. and
this is going to be a whole new chapter
and I have so much more to grow and I
know my best football is ahead of me so
I'm really excited for the opportunity.
>> Hey Fernando, uh Sam Warren with
Athletic. You were just talking about
the legacy of the Raiders. This team has
struggled in recent seasons, had four
straight losing seasons. Um does the
challenge of kind of restoring that
legacy and bringing success back to this
franchise kind of like excite you? Well,
I'm just looking forward to doing my
111th every single play, every single
game, every single season. So, it I'm
I'm just really honored to be a part of
this as a historic franchise and looking
forward to being a small part of the
success in the future.
>> Hey, Fernando, welcome. Taylor Roachcho
with KTNV. Um, yesterday you said that
you were emotional all day. You had to
tell yourself to hold it in. And then
what really broke you was when your mom
told you that she was proud of you. just
why was that and what does it mean for
you to have her in the building with you
here today?
>> It means a lot. Family is everything and
I think it's it's a model of the
Raiders. Once a Raider, always a Raider.
And it means a lot to have my family by
my side, whether it's in Miami or here
in Las Vegas. I'm ecstatic to be a part
of it. The there's a lot of emotions,
especially as a young kid, always wanted
to play in the NFL.
And, you know, finally getting that
call, there's g a lot of emotions, but
it's not about just making the NFL. It's
not the finish line. It's about playing
well in the NFL, lasting long in the
NFL, and making an impact in the NFL.
So, with the support of my family, new
teammates, and coaches, I'm looking
forward to do that.
>> Hey, Fernando. Kevin Bowlinger, Fox 5
Las Vegas. Uh, we often ask John and
Clint their impressions about players
through the draft process. What was your
impression of the Raiders organization
as you went through the draft process?
>> Well, I'll say it was top-notch. When I
came in my top 30 visit, I was blown
away with everybody in the building top
to bottom. You can see for sure trickle
down effect where everyone has a
everyone's first class. Everyone's first
class and that starts with coach
Kubiaak, Mr. Spitech, Mr. Davis, all the
other owners. I'm really excited to be a
part of this organization and just
professionalism and the way that it's
detailed oriented, how they're going to
give incredible effort and just the
process.
>> Hi know Castro News 3. Welcome to Las
Vegas. Um, you and your mom's
relationship is so beautiful and you've
mentioned that she's your why. Is there
a memory you have during a hard time
where she pushed you or a conversation
you guys had to keep following this
dream that you're now living out?
>> Yeah, it was at my third season after my
third season at Berkeley or Cal. I had
just graduated and at that point my mom
always saw more me than I saw myself at
that time. And she essentially pushed me
to take a swing at trying to become a
great NFL player. And that was that
first step was transferring and
challenging myself being an
uncomfortable environment because when
you're uncomfortable, you're able to
grow. and me stepping to the plate. And
she said, "Hey, if you step to the
plate, if you swing and you miss, at
least in 20 years, you knew you did
everything possible to try to accomplish
your dream." And I stepped to the plate.
And luckily enough, I was able to hit a
home run last year. So, she taught me to
have unwavering optimism and that
fortune favors the bold. And you got to
have unwavering optimism to believe in
yourself and then achieve those goals.
>> We're going to wrap it up with Case,
Lindsay, and Harry.
>> Hey, Fernando. Uh, Case Kefir, Las Vegas
son. Uh, we just heard Clint talk about
how impressed he was with your
leadership in the 16-0 season. John said
something similar last night. I'm I'm
guessing that couldn't have been easy
showing up in a new place and doing
that. What was the hardest part about
that? And what did you learn out of that
experience that you can uh bring to the
Raiders as a rookie? Well, I think the
great thing about Indiana last year and
Las Vegas this year is I'm showing up to
a new place with fantastic leaders on
every in every corner of the building,
whether it's offense, defense, special
teams, coaches, operations, owners, you
know, every corner there's fantastic
leaders and I'm excited to be a part of
that and learn from those leaders. And
that's what I did in Indiana. I stepped
in there, try to have the lowest ego
possible, work my butt off, and earn it
because I believe that leadership is
earned. It's not given. And so I look
forward to learning from all the
fantastic people in this organization
and hopefully one day becoming a good
leader.
>> Lindsay Theory with ESPN. Clint, was
there a time through the process that
you just knew for certain that uh
Fernando was your guy? Whether that be,
you know, watching him, observing him at
one of the pro at proday or an
interaction that you had with him.
>> Yeah, when we went to the proday and we
got to see Fernando throw live and the
way he ran that proday and he, you know,
boss his teammates around, told him what
route they were running and how
accurately he threw the ball, uh,
obviously his stature and then took him
upstairs and talked football with them
and just, you know, listened to him
communicate the game and how well how
quickly he picked things up. um very
liked how he played the game on film,
but uh seeing him in person uh was was
really helpful and allowed us to watch
film on a lot of other guys. You know,
we knew who we we knew we had the guy.
>> Fernando, you played in two schools,
Berkeley and Indiana, but you actually
played in three different conferences.
How much did that help you in the
process to become a pro being in three
different styles with the Pack 12, ACC,
and the Big 10? Yeah, not only did I
play in three different conferences, all
four years of college, I've had a new
system and I think it's been a great
opportunity to learn every single year
rather than find myself comfortable.
Evidently, every like every quarterback
and every coach wants to be in a system
for a long time so I can grow in the
system. But that change whether it was
conference systems, it gave me an
opportunity to learn, grow, and
establish a process on how to learn new
systems, which I'm looking forward to
using in this and looking forward to
taking all the coaching I can.
And I just feel like it's made me a
versatile player that I can adapt to new
game plan plays, new systems. I'm really
part excited to learn.
>> Great. Thank you, gentlemen. That
concludes our press conference.
Photographers, please approach the
front. We'll have a quick photo
opportunity.
>> Thank you. God bless. Thank you guys for
coming.